We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Did you know that you can burn off significantly
more body fat exercising before meals,
rather than after them?
Here’s our first story.
What is the optimal exercise
timing for weight loss?
Is it better to exercise
in the morning or the evening?
Before breakfast
or after breakfast?
There was a Nobel Prize-
winning exercise physiologist
who said he always ran a mile
every morning before breakfast.
Was he right? Let’s find out.
More than a dozen experiments
have been published
comparing the amount
of fat burned
in a fasted versus fed state,
and every single one
found more fat was burned
on an empty stomach.
On average, a single bout of low-
to-moderate intensity activity
before a meal burned off
three grams more fat
than the same amount
of exercise after a meal.
That’s about three-quarters
of a pat of butter’s worth of fat,
enough to improve
insulin sensitivity.
The same amount of exercise,
but more fat loss,
all because of timing.
Now, just because you burn
more fat while you’re exercising
doesn’t necessarily
mean you end up
with less fat
at the end of the day.
Maybe your body offsets
the extra fat loss
that occurs during exercise
with a little extra fat storage
when you finally do eat,
balancing it out.
Researchers in Japan set out
to investigate the possibility
that your body makes
up for it later
by measuring 24-hour fat
balance after 100 minutes
of running either before
breakfast or after lunch.
On the exercise-after-lunch day,
they burned a total
of 608 calories of fat
over the course of that day.
In contrast, on the exercise-
before-breakfast days,
in the same 24-hour period
they burned through
nearly 90 percent more,
1,142 calories of straight fat.
So, the next day, they woke up
with about a quarter
cup of fat less
after the same amount
of exercise.
That’s remarkable!
What about just
something like walking?
Sixty minutes before breakfast,
after lunch, or after dinner.
Over the 24 hours
they exercised in the evening,
432 calories were burned off.
On the afternoon exercise day,
they burned off
446 calories of fat.
They also had a control day
with no exercise at all,
and on that day, they burned
through 456 fat calories.
That’s disappointing—it’s like
they never walked at all.
But the same amount
of exercise before breakfast
resulted in 717 calories
of fat loss.
Over the course of a day
timing matters,
so much so that when it
comes to an hour of walking,
exercise increases 24-hour
fat burning only
when it's performed
before breakfast.
All such similar studies
on both men and women
show we burn through more fat
on the days we exercise before,
rather than after eating.
After reading the
chronobiology chapter though
or watching my
chronobiology videos,
an alternative explanation
may spring to mind.
Maybe it’s just a morning thing.
Maybe it has nothing
to do with meals,
and your circadian rhythm
is just dictating the difference.
No. Exercising in the morning
after breakfast
appears no better than exercising
in the evening after dinner,
and exercising before
breakfast works better
than immediately after breakfast,
both still in the morning.
It really does seem to be
a pre- versus post-meal effect.
But why?
Carbohydrate is the preferred
fuel of the body.
When you eat sugars or starches,
they get broken down
and converted into blood sugar.
After a meal, blood sugars rise
and your muscles are quick
to snatch it up for fuel
without having to rely
much on your energy stores.
If you instead take a siesta,
and your muscles have
no immediate need for energy,
the excess blood sugar from a meal
can be stored in our
muscles in the form
of glycogen for later use.
Glycogen is just a bunch
of blood sugar molecules
strung together into
a mass of branches
that can be broken off and used
for quick bursts of energy
any time we need them.
If you exercise after a meal,
your muscles can siphon off
some of the extra blood sugar
floating around for energy.
Before a meal, your
muscles have to instead
resort to dipping
into your energy stores
and end up burning mostly
a combination
of glycogen and fat.
That explains why you burn
more fat during fasted exercise,
but what about all the extra fat
burned throughout
the rest of the day?
Glycogen is more than a store.
Glycogen isn’t just
an energy reserve,
but acts as a sensor capable
of activating metabolic pathways.
Exercising before
breakfast can exhaust
as much as 18 percent
of your glycogen stores,
and that depletion can
act as a powerful rallying cry
to your fatty tissues
to start pulling
more of their own weight
by breaking down more fat.
The lower glycogen
stores fall,
the greater the sustained
24-hour fat loss.
How long do you have
to go without food
in order to trigger this effect?
Six hours may be sufficient;
so, it doesn’t have
to be before breakfast.
If you timed it right, you could
exercise before a late lunch,
or if you have an early enough
lunch, maybe before dinner
when you get home from work.
If exercise in a fasted
state isn’t possible,
does it matter what you eat?
Insulin release after a meal
appears to play a critical role
in suppressing fat breakdown,
explaining why lower
glycemic foods
can have less of an effect.
Lentils were identified
as a promising option
for maintaining
athletic endurance
(which can take a hit
on an empty stomach)
while maintaining more
of the fat dissolution.
Lentils are said to be
unlikely to be consumed
by the general population
due to 'low palatability".
They obviously haven’t tried
my mom’s lentil soup.
It's worth mentioning
that although
there’s increased 24-hour
fat burning exercising
in a fasted state,
the only way to see
if this facilitates
weight loss over time
is to put it to the test,
which we’ll explore next.
A systematic review and
meta-analysis on exercise timing
for fat metabolism found
that exercising
in a completely fasted
state may work best.
The Japanese team that published
some of the seminal work
in this area went
as far as to assert:
“If exercise were
a pill to burn body fat,
it would be effective only
when taken before breakfast.”
Surveys show few people exercise
before breakfast, though.
Before asking people
to make the switch,
we need to make sure that these
tantalizing 24-hour results
translate into weight loss
over the long-term.
There’s a solid theoretical basis,
but you don’t know until...
you put it to the test.
In a study of experimental
weight gain,
volunteers were fed up to
4,500 calories a day for six weeks
while vigorously exercising
a total of 300 minutes a week,
either always after an overnight
fast or after a meal.
A control group who didn’t exercise
at all gained about 6.5 pounds,
compared to 3 pounds in the
exercise-after-a-meal group.
The pre-meal exercise group
worked out the same amount,
but only gained about half
as much—1 3/4 pounds.
What about weight loss, though?
Twenty young women
were randomized
into three hours
a week of before
or after a meal exercise.
Same diets, same
amount of exercise, and...
disappointingly, about
same amount of weight loss.
The pre-meal exercise group
did lose about an extra pound
of body fat (total weight loss
3.5 lbs. vs. 2.2 lbs.),
but this did not reach
statistical significance,
meaning such a small
difference could very well
have been due to chance.
A study of six weeks
of low volume, high intensity
interval training
before or after meals
similarly failed
to show a difference.
One explanation that’s
been offered for this failure
is that the increased fat loss
during premeal exercise
might be “neutralized”
by the lesser
diet-induced thermogenesis.
In other words, because it costs
our body fewer calories
to process food if we eat after
compared to before physical activity.
When we exercise after a meal
our body gets mixed signals.
Exercise is all about mobilizing
energy stores for fuel,
whereas eating is more about
assimilation and storage,
and the metabolic
challenge presented
by the ensuing
“hormonal tug-of-war”
might be responsible for the 15
to 40 percent greater calorie cost.
This has led some
to recommend exercising
after meals to facilitate
weight loss.
If you do the math, though,
our body is so efficient
at digesting that the 15 percent
to 40 percent increase
might only come out
to be 3 to 12 calories.
Such a slight difference
would be easily overwhelmed
by the huge disparity in fat loss,
as confirmed by the 24-hour
fat balance studies,
showing up to 500 calories
of fat-burning difference.
I would suggest
a more reasonable
explanation might
be that the clear
body fat deficit on pre-meal
exercise days
is made up for by extra fat
storage on non-exercise days.
Your body likes to hold on
to extra body fat if it can,
and so on days
you’re not driving it down
it may try to even things out.
Both of the failed
weight loss studies
had people exercising
only three days a week,
and so, their bodies had most
of the week to compensate.
The study I’d like
to see is a pre-meal
vs. post-meal exercise on all
or at least most days
of the week
to see if we can continue
to drive down fat stores.
For those with diabetes, though,
you’d want to do the opposite.
You can imagine how
that siphoning effect muscles
have on excess blood
sugar during exercise
might be great for those suffering
from elevated blood sugars.
And indeed, exercising
after a meal
can bring down blood sugars
as well as some blood
sugar-lowering drugs.
Randomize type 2 diabetics
to a 20-minute leisurely stroll
(about 2 mph) before dinner
versus after dinner,
and the after-dinner
group blunted
their blood sugar
spike 30 percent.
Same meal, same amount
of exercise,
but a significant effect
on blood sugar control
thanks to a little
tactical timing.
Even just a 10-minute walk
after a meal may
make a difference.
So, for those with
blood sugar problems,
it’s better to exercise
after meals than before them.
Blood sugar from a meal starts
appearing in the bloodstream
15 to 20 minutes
after the first bite
and is ramping
up by 30 minutes
to peak at around
the one-hour mark
before declining to premeal
levels within a few hours.
So, for optimal
blood sugar control,
prediabetics and diabetics
should start exercising
30 minutes after
the start of a meal
and ideally go for an hour
to completely straddle
the blood sugar peak.
If you had to choose a single
meal to exercise after,
it would be dinner,
due to the circadian rhythm
of blood sugar control
that wanes throughout the day.
Ideally, then, breakfast would be
the largest meal of the day
and you’d exercise after that,
or exercise after every meal.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.